Finding aid to the Ruth E. Young Papers CA.MS.00401
Smith College Archives
Ruth E. Young Papers
1925-1983
Smith College Archives
Young, Ruth Elizabeth
CA.MS.00401
0.417 linear feet (1 container)
Contains correspondence, news clippings, photographs, publications, pamphlets, Rations books, curriculum vitae, certificates and invitations from the professional papers of Ruth E. Young, Professor of Italian.
Biographical / Historical
Ruth E. Young was born in Escanaba, Michigan, to Roscoe Cyprian and Cora Ella (Cox) Young in 1896. She received her Ph.B. from the University of Chicago in 1918 and, after taking several years off from school to teach English and French at Suomi College, she returned to receive A.M. from the University in 1923. From 1923-1924, Young attended the University of Florence, returning to teach in the Home-Study faculty and Italian Faculty of the University. In In 1925, Young left the University of Chicago to become part of the Smith College Italian Language and Literature Faculty, where she remained until her retirement in 1961. At Smith, Young taught and wrote on medieval and Renaissance Italy, as well as taking on administrative roles, including Dean of the Class of 1945 and Director of Smith Junior Year Abroad in Italy sporadically from 1933 until 1956. Young was also active outside the college, serving as a member of the U.S. Armed Forces Institute and as a volunteer for the Office of Strategic Services during World War II, and as a relief worker in Italy with World Student Relief in 1945-1946. She was also a member of the editorial board for the new Dante language concordance prepared by the Dante Society of America, the Director of the New England section of the Modern Languages Association, and the Vice-President of the American Association of Teachers of Italian. She was awarded the Order of Merit of the Republic with the rank of Cavaliere by the Italian Government in 1960 for her work building understanding between the U.S. and Italy. Young died in Florida Lutheran Retirement Home in 1983.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the professional papers of Ruth E. Young from her time teaching at Smith until her death in 1983. The collection contains a mix of materials, including several of her publications, news clippings about her career and life, certificates and other memorabilia, a photo album from Junior Year Abroad in Italy 1936-1937, and pamphlets and recollections of World Student Relief, but the majority of the collection is taken up with letters of condolence after the death of Blanche Mitchell.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Young, Ruth Elizabeth
- General, 1925-1983 (Box 1108, Folder 1)
- Correspondence: General, 1946 (Box 1108, Folder 2)
- Correspondence: Baum, Charlotte, Class of 1915, 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 3)
- Correspondence: Campbell, Kathleen, 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 4)
- Correspondence: Clark, Annetta Isabel, Class of 1904, 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 5)
- Correspondence: Ainsworth, Dorothy Sears, Class of 1916, 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 6)
- Correspondence: Dillon, George, 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 7)
- Correspondence: Farrand, Margaret Louise, Class of 1914, undated (Box 1108, Folder 8)
- Correspondence: Foster, Elizabeth Andros, 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 9)
- Correspondence: Goldsmith, Margaret, undated (Box 1108, Folder 10)
- Correspondence: Hill, Edith Naomi, Class of 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 11)
- Correspondence: Hill, Ruth Elizabeth, 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 12)
- Correspondence: McElwain, Mary Belle, 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 13)
- Correspondence: Mac Murphy, Ann G., undated (Box 1108, Folder 14)
- Correspondence: Mitchell, Blanche, Class of 1914, 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 15)
- Correspondence: Mitchell, Mrs. Emlyn V., 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 16)
- Correspondence: Robinson, Edith Anne, Class of 1930, 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 17)
- Correspondence: Smith, Elizabeth (Hugus), Class of 1915, undated (Box 1108, Folder 18)
- Correspondence: Soby, Eleanor Kyburg, 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 19)
- Correspondence: Vezzetti, Anacleta Candida, 1933 (Box 1108, Folder 20)
- Correspondence: Vorencamp, Alfons P.A., undated (Box 1108, Folder 21)
- Junior Year Abroad, 1933-1934 (Box 1108, Folder 22)
- Photographs, undated (Box 1108, Folder 23)
- Photographs: Abruzzi, 1945; undated (Box 1108, Folder 24)
- Publications: Baldassare Castiglione and Il Cortegiano, 1938 (Box 1108, Folder 25)
- Publications: Borgese, Giuseppe A. to Mussolini, undated (Box 1108, Folder 26)
- Publications: Borgese, Giuseppe A. to Short Stories, 1937 (Box 1108, Folder 27)
- Publications: Introduction to Castiglione and his Courtier, 1940 (Box 1108, Folder 28)
- Publications: Translation of "The Liar", undated (Box 1108, Folder 29)
- World Student Relief, 1945-1946 (Box 1108, Folder 30)
- World Student Relief: Yugoslavia, 1945 (Box 1108, Folder 31)
- World Student Relief: Recollections, 1979 (Box 1108, Folder 32)
- Photo Album, 1936-1937 (Box 1108, Folder 33)